Marguerite Wildenhain
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Marguerite Wildenhain papers
1930-1982
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Wildenhain, Marguerite
3.4 linear feet
The papers of California ceramicist and educator Marguerite Wildenhain measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1982. Found within the papers are biographical sketches; correspondence with patrons, students, and colleagues, including Eugene Anderson, T. S. Eliot, and Gerhard Marcks; writings by Wildenhain and others; designs for pottery and other artwork; one scrapbook; news clippings, exhibition catalogs, and scattered printed material. Also found are photographs of Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain, Pond Farm, workshops, exhibitions,and artwork, as well as two film reels depicting Wildenhain lecturing and in her studio.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Marguerite Wildenhain in 1973-1981.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art are the Marguerite Wildenhain exhibition records, 1977-1981, donated by the Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art; an oral history interview of Marguerite Wildenhain conducted 1982 Mar. 14, by Hazel Bray; and the Frans Wildenhain papers, 1890-1986. Additional Marguerite Wildenhain letters to Gerhard Marcks are located at the Archiv fur Buldende Kunst of the Germanisches Museum, Nurnberg, Germany.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 5045-5048 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Use of video requires an appointment.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Marguerite Wildenhain (1896-1985) was a ceramicist and educator in Guerneville, California. Born Marguerite Friedlaender in Lyon, France, Wildenhain received training in sculpture at the Berlin School of Applied Arts. She later worked as a designer for the Royal Berlin Porcelain Factory, leaving in 1919 to apprentice in pottery at the Bauhaus, under Max Krehan and Gerhard Marcks. After receiving her degree as master-potter, she was employed at the Municipal School for Arts and Crafts in Halle Saale, Germany. Fleeing the Nazis in 1933, she and her husband, potter Frans Wildenhain, operated a workshop in Holland before immigrating to the United States in 1940. In 1942 she settled near Guerneville, California, and established an artist colony known as Pond Farm. Following her divorce, she remained at Pond Farm and operated a summer school which lasted until 1980, training approximately 25 students each summer.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of California ceramicist and educator Marguerite Wildenhain measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1982. Found within the papers are biographical sketches; correspondence with patrons, students, and colleagues, including Eugene Anderson, T. S. Eliot, and Gerhard Marcks; writings by Wildenhain and others; designs for pottery and other artwork; one scrapbook; news clippings, exhibition catalogs, and scattered printed material. Also found are photographs of Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain, Pond Farm, workshops, exhibitions,and artwork, as well as two film reels depicting Wildenhain lecturing and in her studio.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1943 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1940-1981 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1940-1980 (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 4: Artwork, circa 1961-1969, 1975 (Box 2, OV 5; 4 folders)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1934-1963 (Box 2; 3 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1932-1982 (Box 2, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1930-1976 (Box 2-4; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Audio-Visual Recordings, 1954, circa 1965 (Box 3, 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Wildenhain, Frans, 1905-
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Study and teaching--California; Artists' studios--California--Photographs; Ceramicists--California; Women artists
Types of Materials:
Designs; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs; Scrapbooks; Video recordings
Names:
Anderson, Eugene Newton; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Marcks, Gerhard
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1943, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  A folder of biographical material from 1943 consists of four biographical sketches.
  - Biographical Material, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1940-1981, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  Correspondence is with patrons, students, and colleagues including Eugene Anderson, T. S. Eliot, and Gerhard Marcks. One letter, Mar. 3, 1980, from Marcks contains a photograph of Wildenhain and other German potters. Sixty-six letters are in German.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1965, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence, 1966, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1967, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Correspondence, 1975, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence, 1976, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Writings, circa 1940-1980, Series 3:; (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
  Writings includes notes and lists of museum exhibition and lecture sites, collectors, and students. Also found are essays and lectures by Wildenhain as well as typescripts for her books Pottery: Form and Expression, The Invisible Core, and ...That We Look and See: An Admirer Looks at the Indian. There are also two short essays by others about Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain.
  - Miscellaneous Lists, undated, 1952-1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Development of the Pond Farm Pottery and School," undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Pond Farm Pottery in Guerneville, California," undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Introduction to Movie on Pond Farm," undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lecture, "Design and its Relation to Techniques," undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "First Report of the Educational Committee of the Designer-Craftmen of California on Education in the Arts and Crafts," undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Lecture, "The Pursuit of Excellence in Art Education," undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Elements of Design," undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "?For it is a Continuous Process," undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "To Leonora," undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Lecture, "Philosophy of a Potter," undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Pottery," undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Thoughts on Pricing and Selling Pottery," undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Lecture, "History of Pottery-Making," 1940 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - [A School of Art Teaching Ceramics], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Pottery as a Craft in the Machine Age," 1947 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - [To Learn a Craft], 1949 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Lecture, "Ceramic Design or the Relation of Craftsman to Industry," 1950 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lecture, "Craft and Industry," 1950 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Pottery as a Creative Craft," 1950 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Lecture, "Hand Made Pottery in the Machine Age," 1951 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Lecture, "The Potter in the New World," 1952 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Lecture, "Open Letter to Bernhard Leach," 1953 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Lecture, "what Makes a Potter Good," 1953 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "Color in Ceramics," 1954 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Lecture, "Form and Technique," 1955 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Lecture, [Interaction between Client and Craftsman], 1956 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Design and its Relation to Techniques," 1957 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Lecture, "Socio-economic Outlook for the Craftsman Today," 1957 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Lecture, "Art Education in Our Time," 1958 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Lecture, "External Pressures on Creativity," 1958 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Lecture, "Nature as a Source of Inspiration," 1960 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - "Production and Integrity," 1960 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Lecture, "Shaping the Clay," 1962 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Lecture: "Vision in Art," 1963 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "Creative Freedom and Integrity," 1965 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Drafts of Book Pottery: Form and Expression, 1957, (7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 70-76)
  - Drafts of Book The Invisible Core, 1965-1972, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 77-79)
  - Drafts of Book The Invisible Core, 1965-1972, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Drafts of Book ?That We Look and See: An Admirer Looks at the Indian, 1975-1979, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
  - Writings by Others regarding Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Artwork, circa 1961-1969, 1975, Series 4:; (Box 2, OV 5; 4 folders)
  Artwork consists of designs for pottery, a floorplan, and a diagram of a kick wheel. Also found are a folder of drawings which include a 1975 note by Marguerite Wildenhain which reads, "25 drawings that have, more or less, inspired me for pots, tiles or sculptures."
  - Designs for Pottery, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Drawings of Floorplan and Kickwheel, undated, (Oversized material housed in OV 5) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Drawings, 1961-1969, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Oversize Drawings of Floorplan and Kickwheel, undated, (Oversized material from Box 2, folder 15) (Box OV 5)
- Scrapbooks, 1934-1963, Series 5:; (Box 2; 3 folders)
  One scrapbook contains clippings, exhibition announcements, and a photograph of art work.
  - Scrapbooks, 1934-1963, (3 folders; disbound) (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
- Printed Material, circa 1932-1982, Series 6:; (Box 2, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
  Printed material includes numerous clippings documenting Wildenhain's career, exhibition announcements and catalogs, a press release, brochures concerning Wildenhain and pottery classes, and books, including ...That We Look and See: An Admirer Looks at the Indians by Wildenhain.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Press Release, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Brochures regarding Marguerite Wildenhain, 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Brochures regarding Pottery Classes and Seminars, 1953-1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1952-1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Book, Kleine Bauhaus-Fibel by Hans Wingler, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Book, ?That We Look and See: An Admirer Looks at the Indian by Wildenhhain, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Photographs, 1930-1976, Series 7:; (Box 2-4; 1.2 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain, Marguerite Wildenhain in her home and studio at Pond Farm, art works, and exhibition installations. Also found is a family photograph album which includes photographs from France, Germany, and Holland.
  - Marguerite Wildenhain, 1940-1973, (Oversized material housed in Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Family Album, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain, 1930-1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Slides, Marguerite and Frans Wildenhain, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Marguerite Wildenhain conducting her Pond Farm Workshop, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pond Farm, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Slides, Pond Farm and Workshop, 1942-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Slides, Wildenhain Demonstrating Pot-throwing, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Art Work Produced in Germany 1926-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Album, Art Works (Disbound), undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Art Works Executed 1952-1972 [photos by David Stone], undated, (10 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-18)
  - Art Works Marked with Plate Numbers, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Art Works, undated, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 20-26)
  - Slides of Art Works, 1965-1969, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
  - Art Work, T.S. Eliot Vase "Murder in the Cathedral", 1951 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Art Works, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Slides, Miscellaneous Art Work, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Slides, Works in the Smithsonian Collection, undated, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Slides, Works from Collection of Carol McFarlan, Petaluma, Cal., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Installation, College of Education, Great Falls, Montana, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Installation, San Francisco Museum of Art, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Installation, Detroit Institute of Arts, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Exhibition Installations, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Oversize Photographs of Marguerite Wildenhain, 1940-1973, (Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 36) (Box 4)
- Audio-Visual Recordings, 1954, circa 1965, Series 8:; (Box 3, 4; 0.3 linear feet)
  The audio-visual material consists of two 16 mm film reels entitled "From a Lump of Clay" (called "Pond Farm" on the duplicate VHS videocassette), recording Wildenhain at work, and "Scripps College," recording a lecture by Wildenhain. Both films have been transferred onto one VHS videocassette.
  - "Scripps College" and "Pond Farm [From a Lump of Clay]" 1954, circa 1965, (1 videocassette: VHS) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - "Scripps College," 1954, (1 film reel) (Box 4)
  - "From a Lump of Clay," circa 1965, (1 film reel) (Box 4)